TOEI STATION
(東榮站)
TOEI, KITASHITARA DISTRICT, AICHI PREFECTURE
(東榮 愛知縣北設樂郡東榮町)
You've come a long way, Rin.
辛苦妳遠道而來了 凜
Is there anywhere you want to visit?
有什麼想去的地方嗎
The dam.
水壩
The dam?
水壩？
The dam it is.
那就去看看吧
ELEMENTARY 4TH GRADE SOCIAL STUDIES
(小學社會4年級)
WHERE DOES THE WATER FLOW?
(水會從哪裡流向哪裡呢)
Looks like we came at the right time.
看來我們來得正是時候呢
Come here.
來 過來這裡
Is it scary?
妳會害怕嗎
A little.
有點害怕
But it's fascinating.
但是 很有趣
I see.
這樣啊
Welcome.
歡迎光臨
INABU CASTELLA, MATCHA, BLACK RICE
(稻武蜂蜜蛋糕 抹茶 黑米)
Do you know what you're going to include in your journal?
想好該怎麼寫繪圖日記了嗎
INABU LOCAL SPECIALITIES
(稻武特產品區)
"INABU ONSEN, INABU WORKSHOP" Thank you for your purchase.
(稻武之湯 稻武工房) 謝謝惠顧
All right. Let's head back to my place.
好了 我們回爺爺家吧
These are camping supplies.
這些是露營道具
Camping?
露營？
LAID-BACK CAMP SEASON 3
《搖曳露營△ (第三季)》
EPISODE ONE: WHERE ARE WE GOING NEXT?
(第1話 下次要去哪裡呢)
LAKE SHOJIKO
(精進湖)
Doesn't that little mountain look like a small child?
面前那座小山是不是很像小孩子？
Because it looks like Mount Fuji holding a child in its arms,
由於看起來很像富士山 抱著一個小孩子
this scene is called "Kodakifuji" (Fuji cradling a child).
因此這副景象被稱為"抱子富士"
You're right.
真的耶
It does look like Mount Fuji's holding a child.
看起來好像在抱小孩
And the only lake where you can see the inverted Fuji cradling a child
而唯一能看到抱子富士的 逆富士的湖
is Lake Shojiko.
就只有精進湖了
Inverted Fuji?
逆富士？
Yes.
是啊
But now there are ripples on the lake surface, so you can't see it.
不過現在湖面上有波紋 所以看不到
Anyway, this is your reserved camping site.
那麼 您預約的營位在這裡
Okay.
謝謝
All right.
好
I'm good at pitching tents now.
我已經很會搭帳棚了
The tent I got from Grandpa
從爺爺那邊收到的帳篷
is getting a bit old.
有點變舊了呢
So, all of those are Grandpa's?
原來那些全都是爺爺的啊
Do you want to try camping?
妳想去露營看看嗎
Camping?
露營…
Camping is that thing, right?
露營就是那個吧？
I've seen it on TV before.
我之前有在電視上看過
Just do this and you can start a fire, right?
只要這樣用一用就能點火吧？
Or was that a movie?
是在電影看到的嗎
They rub their hands like this and smoke comes out.
只要這樣用一用就會開始冒煙
Grandpa, can you do that too?
爺爺 你也會用那個嗎
Um, that's a little…
不是 呃 那有點…
You can't?
爺爺辦不到嗎
All right.
好
What's the matter?
怎麼了嗎
TSUGU PARK
(津具公園)
Cold?
會不會冷？
No.
不會
Hello!
妳好
Grandpa, isn't this how you do it?
爺爺 不是這樣用的嗎
You can do it that way,
雖然那樣也可以
but I want to show you another way.
但我想讓凜看看別種方法
Don't worry.
放心吧
This will make a fire too.
這樣也點得起來
I've never tried this way, though.
雖然我沒有試過
Until that day,
在那天之前
I always thought Grandpa was a scary man,
我一直覺得爺爺很可怕
so I didn't know how to get along with him.
因此不太擅長和他相處呢
Maybe I should try that.
要不要來試試那個呢？
This is how you do it, right?
這樣做應該是正確的吧？
It's smoking!
冒煙了
Hot!
好燙
It's lit.
點燃囉
That's amazing!
好厲害
Should we heat up the milk we just bought
剛才買的牛奶 要不要加熱成熱牛奶呢？
I think…
我好像…
I made Grandpa
讓爺爺做了
do something absurd
既荒唐
and impossible.
又不合理的事
It's smoking!
冒煙了
Just a little more!
再加把勁
My arms are killing me…
手臂…要死了
There's smoke,
明明冒煙了
but it just won't catch fire at all.
但卻完全點不著火
I did it!
有了
That's amazing!
好厲害
Ready…
預備…
Be careful, it's hot.
現在還很燙 要小心一點喔
It's nice and warm.
熱熱的好好喝
All right.
那麼
Let's take this cup of milk
我們拿著這杯牛奶
and head to my secret spot.
去爺爺私藏的秘密景點吧
Miss,
大姊姊
you went through all that work to start a fire.
妳明明好不容易才點燃火
But why did you use this to cook?
為什麼要用這個煮呢？
If you cook with an open fire,
如果用篝火煮
the charcoal will make the pot turn black.
鍋子會被炭燻黑的
Hana-chan, it's time to go!
小花 該走囉
I don't want to go home yet.
我還不想回去
Come on. Your dad's waiting in the car.
好啦 爸爸已經在車上等我們了
No, I want to stay.
不要 人家還想玩啦
Now, now...
哎呀
It's a nice view, isn't it?
這裡的風景很不錯吧？
Yum.
好好吃
Want another?
要再吃一個嗎
Can I have it?
可以嗎
Yes, I'm full.
因為爺爺已經很飽了
INABU OBSERVATION POINT
(稻武觀景台)
Let's pack up after you finish your snack.
吃完後 我們就準備回家吧
Don't make that face.
不要露出那種表情
Loneliness always accompanies camping.
露營總會伴隨著寂寞
And it's this loneliness that makes us look forward
也正是因為有這份寂寞
to the next camping trip.
才會期待下一次的露營喔
SCENIC LOOKOUT ROUTE
(觀景台路線)
We can go on another trip another day.
只要改天再去就好了
I always feel
總覺得
a bit lonely at the end of each trip.
每趟旅程結束時 都會覺得有點寂寞呢
But
但是
I don't dislike that feeling.
我不討厭那種感覺喔
After all, I can just go on another trip
畢竟只要改天再去就好了
somewhere else, another day.
去其他地方
But still,
但是
I can't help feeling a bit lonely
果然還是會覺得有點寂寞呢
because of how much fun we've had over these past few days.
因為 這幾天過得很開心啊
It's this loneliness that makes us look forward
正因為有這份寂寞
to the next camping trip, huh?
才會期待下一次的露營…嗎
Nadeshiko, where should we go next time?
撫子 下次要去哪裡呢？
OUTDOOR ACTIVITIES CLUB
(野外活動同好會)
It's been a while since we've hung out together after school.
總覺得我們好像很久 沒在放學後聚在一起了呢
It's because we've all been so busy with work.
因為最近都在拚命打工呀
Exactly!
就是說啊
We've been working too hard.
我們太拚命打工了啦
The money we got from our part-time jobs
雖然打工費確實讓我們買了椅子
did let us buy the camping chairs and go on that luxurious Izu Camp, though.
還體驗了一場超豪華的伊豆露營
And lots of souvenirs.
也買了很多伴手禮呢
That was a fun trip.
那幾天真的很開心呢
But
但是
have you forgotten what we set out to do?
妳們是不是忘記我們的初衷了？
Even without spending any money,
就算不花錢
we've come up with lots of things with our brilliant minds and trial and error!
我們不也靠自己的腦袋 透過反覆嘗試做出了許多道具嗎
But
可是
the makeshift bed was a failure.
睡袋那次失敗了喔
Shh, let's not bring that up.
噓 別提那件事了
Therefore,
綜上所述
for this long-awaited after-school Outdoor Activities Club meeting,
這場久違的放學後野外活動同好會
"PREMIUM CAFÉ AU LAIT" we will be having this!
(超好喝的咖啡歐蕾) 要用這個
Drink up.
好了 喝吧…
Thanks.
謝謝
Is this your treat?
這是請我們的嗎
We're going to make alcohol stoves with these!
今天我們要用這個空罐子做酒精爐
That's an alcohol lamp.
那是酒精燈
Alcohol stove.
酒精爐
A type of portable stove that uses alcohol as fuel
這是一種以酒精為燃料
and is extremely lightweight.
並且非常輕巧的攜帶型火爐
Typically used when mountain climbing or solo camping.
主要用於登山或獨自露營時
It can be used to boil water
可以用來煮熱水 或是煮一些簡單的料理
Because of its simple construction,
由於構造很簡單
it can also be made using empty cans.
因此也能用空罐子自己做
I've read about it in outdoor magazines.
偶爾會在戶外雜誌上看到呢
I didn't know you can make one yourself.
原來也可以自己做啊
Gleam!
閃亮
DISCARD THIS PART, MAKE A CUT HERE
(這裡丟掉 記得留切口)
"USE A COMPASS KNIFE, USE AN AWL" Here's how you make it.
(用圓規刀 用錐子) 關於做法嘛
"ROLL UP AND INSERT, AND DONE" Cut the can in half,
(塞進去 捲起來放進去 完成) 只要把鋁罐切半
punch some holes,
打洞
and stick it all together.
再塞在一起就好了
You make it sound so simple.
妳也說得太簡單扼要了吧
That's all there is to it!
它就是這麼簡單喔
"FIZZY GRAPE DRINK" Incidentally,
(噗滋噗滋葡萄飲料) 順帶一提
when using aluminium cans as materials,
用來當材料的鋁罐
avoid using ones with labels directly printed on the can.
不要用直接把標籤印在表面的那種
Choosing cans with stick-on labels
選標籤是用貼上去的罐子
will yield better results.
成效會比較好
Maybe we can make
如果用長一點的罐子做
a long-burning alcohol stove if we use longer cans!
或許可以做出一個 能長時間燃燒的酒精爐呢
That sounds dangerous. Just follow the instructions.
那樣會很危險 給我按照指示做
And so, they got right to it.
於是她們馬上開始試做了
Wrap masking tape around the can, then gently cut along the edges
像這樣用紙膠帶纏在罐子上當基準
with a knife repeatedly.
然後輕輕地用刀子反覆在邊緣切割
That will give you nice, clean cuts.
似乎就能切得很漂亮喔
I see.
原來如此
FIRST CAN
(第一個)
SECOND CAN
(第二個)
THIRD CAN
(第三個)
No matter what I do, it always caves in when I cut it!
不管試幾次 都會在切的時候就被我壓扁了
We just started...
這才剛開始耶
Nadeshiko's using too much force.
撫子太用力了啦
In that case...
既然如此
"GRAPE MILK" I'll use a steel can!
(葡萄牛奶) 那我就用鋼罐做
This time it won't cut at all!
這次連切都切不開了
Sheesh!
真是的
"HACKSAW" I'll use this hacksaw
(鋼鋸) 那我就用這個鋸子
and saw it in half!
把它鋸成一半
She's really full of energy.
真是精力旺盛啊
By the way, Aki,
話說回來 小明
your hair's gotten pretty long, huh?
妳的頭髮變長了不少啊？
Now that you mention it, it is kind of long.
這麼說起來 好像真的變長了呢
Well, it's been a while since I got a haircut.
畢竟我有一陣子沒剪頭髮了呀
AKI-CHAN
(小明)
The exposed forehead's more Aki's style.
總覺得露出額頭的造型 比較有小明的感覺呢
True.
確實
Should I put it up like this?
那麼 要梳成這樣嗎
That makes you look like my sister.
好像我姊姊
Her hair used to be shoulder-length.
之前好像都只留到肩膀吧
Is that so?
這樣啊
My hair's been a pain
最近去露營時 都會覺得這頭髮很礙事
Maybe it's time to cut it short?
要不要久違地一刀剪成短髮呢
Shall I cut it for you, then?
那麼 需要我幫忙剪嗎
Ena.
惠那
What are you guys making?
妳們在做什麼呀？
We're making alcohol stoves.
我們在做酒精爐喔
Ena, you know how to cut hair?
是說惠那 妳還會剪頭髮嗎
You could say that.
姑且會喔
I cut Chikuwa's fur.
因為竹輪的毛都是我剪的
Oh, Chikuwa.
原來是剪竹輪嗎
Don't worry.
放心啦…
I cut my own hair too.
我也會幫自己剪頭髮
I can totally help you with yours.
我真的可以幫妳剪喔？
Really?
真的嗎
Speaking of a haircut,
剪頭髮
I just had a thought!
我突然想到一件事
Wouldn't it be nice to get your hair cut while you're out camping?
妳們不覺得邊露營 邊剪頭髮挺不錯的嗎
The wide open space at the camping site
如果能在寬廣的露營場剪頭髮
would feel nice, wouldn't it?
那種開放感應該很棒呢
That does sound pretty nice!
聽起來滿舒服的嘛
Right?
對吧？
No, no, no…
不…
The slightest breeze will get the hair everywhere.
一旦起風 剪下來的頭髮就會亂飛
That's not going to work.
我想應該行不通的
Oh, right.
果然沒辦法嗎
In that case, why don't we do it in my yard?
-可以嗎？ -那麼 要不要在我家的庭院剪？
If we'll all be there, why don't we make it a yard camp?
既然都要來 不如就在庭院搭個帳篷吧
Camping in a yard? Yard camp?
在庭院露營？庭院露營？
Yard camp and day camp.
庭院露營兼一日露營
Day yard camp.
合起來就是一日庭院露營
A day yard camp!
一日庭院露營
Then, just carefully insert the bottom half into the top half...
接著只要小心地把罐子的 下半部塞進上半部裡
"DIY ALCOHOL STOVE" DIY alcohol stove
(自製酒精爐) 自製酒精爐
complete!
完成了
As expected of a steel can. Nadeshiko's alcohol stove is sturdy.
不愧是用鋼罐做的 撫子的酒精爐真堅固呢
Right?
對吧
I polished the outer layer too.
而且我還把表面磨得很平整 完全看不出它原本是個果汁罐吧
You did well.
很棒…
Now, let's get Ms. Toba here and start experimenting!
那麼 趕緊叫老師過來做實驗吧
SCIENCE CLASSROOM
(理科教室)
Oh, you girls made alcohol stoves.
妳們做了酒精爐啊
We want
所以 我們現在想把酒精倒進去
and see if they work.
測試看看是否能順利使用
I understand.
我知道了
Let's try it.
來試試看吧
"ANHYDROUS ALCOHOL, 1000 YEN" The main fuels
(無水乙醇1000圓) (燃料用酒精300圓) 倒進酒精爐頭的燃料
are anhydrous alcohol and ethanol fuel.
主要會用燃料用酒精和無水乙醇
Both can be purchased at drugstores.
這兩種在藥妝店都買得到
Additionally,
除此之外
although high-proof alcohol can be used as fuel...
雖然度數高的酒 姑且也能當作燃料使用…
That's too wasteful!
太浪費了
As such, it is not recommended.
因此不建議使用
How much fuel you put in the alcohol stove determines how long it burns,
因為酒精爐裡放多少燃料 就會燒多久
so I'll only pour a little bit.
所以我只倒一點點喔
This is just like a science experiment!
簡直就像在做理科實驗呢
Okay, I'm lighting them up!
那麼 我要點火囉
Huh, are they really lit?
咦 真的有點著嗎
I did hear a sound just now.
剛才是有聽到聲音啦
They're lit.
有點著喔
But the flames are not that noticeable at first.
只是剛開始燃燒時 會比較難看到火焰
You're right!
真的耶
They are burning!
確實有在燃燒
The sunlight outshines the flames.
原來陽光會讓火焰變得不起眼啊
Take a good look.
妳們看好囉
As the heat from the flame warms up the alcohol stoves,
當火焰的熱度讓酒精爐變暖後
the fuel will continuously vaporise.
燃料會不斷氣化
It's so pretty!
好漂亮喔
The holes you make affect the shape of the flame,
因為打洞的方法會影響火焰的形狀
so with practice, you can make some impressive alcohol stoves.
所以講求精緻的人 也能做出很厲害的酒精爐喔
Like works of art.
好像工藝品喔
Ms. Toba, you seem to know a lot about alcohol stoves.
老師 妳對酒精爐很瞭解耶
I've made some before myself.
因為我以前也自己做過
Um...
那個
I hate to say this after all the effort you put into making these,
畢竟妳們都做好了 我也覺得很難以啟齒
but
不過老實說 我希望妳們不要用酒精爐
But why?
這是為什麼呢？
If you put it on grass and accidentally knock it over,
因為如果在草地上用 結果不小心打翻…
the fire could spread quickly, and that can be very dangerous.
火勢會一下子蔓延開來 很危險的
You also need to be careful when storing and transporting the fuel.
還得小心地保存和運送燃料
If you're planning on using alcohol stoves,
如果妳們今後想使用酒精爐
make sure to store the fuel in specialised containers.
一定要把燃料裝在專用容器裡
And be sure to use it on ground where it won't catch fire if spilled.
而且要在打翻也不會燒起來的 土地上使用
Also, be careful not to place flammable materials nearby.
還要小心千萬別把易燃物 放在附近喔
Got it.
知道了
Next time, we'll be at Ena's place for some day yard camping!
下次就是在惠那家的庭院 一日露營了呢
Yard camping and day camping,
是說 庭院露營和一日露營
they're both firsts for me.
我都是第一次體驗呢
It's been a while since I've seen Chikuwa. I'm really looking forward to it.
好久沒見到竹輪了 真期待呢
I've got all of Chikuwa's camping equipment ready to go.
竹輪用的露營道具也全部買齊了 我會拿出來展示的
Please do!
一定要展示給我們看喔
Since we have this opportunity,
難得有這個機會
how about trying to cook something with the alcohol stove?
要不要用酒精爐煮個什麼試試？
Sounds good.
感覺不錯耶
The flames aren't that strong.
畢竟它的火力也不強
We should grill up some sausages.
乾脆來烤些香腸吧
Good idea.
是啊
Izu Camp was fun,
雖然伊豆露營很有趣
but I'm excited for this day camp!
但一日露營也很令人期待呢
Yard camp and day camp and sausage camp.
庭院露營兼一日露營兼香腸露營
Put it together and you get "yard day sausage camp".
合起來就是一日庭院香腸露營呢
You don't have to call it that.
也不用硬要合在一起啦
Nadeshiko!
撫子
The flowers aren't in bloom yet.
現在還沒開花吧 妳在拍什麼啊？
Sorry to keep you guys waiting.
抱歉 讓妳們久等了
It's been a while, Rin.
小凜 好久不見
IT'S BEEN A WHILE, RIN
(小凜 好久不見) (不好意思 請問妳是誰？)
Oh, sorry. It's Ayano. Send!
抱歉…我是綾乃啦 傳送
NEXT EPISODE: PETIT CAMP AND YARD CAMP
(下集 小露營和庭院露營)
WHEN ENJOYING CAMPING,
(享受露營時… ) (務必遵守露營場和其設施的規定)
DON'T FORGET TO PUT OUT YOUR CAMPFIRE AND DISPOSE OF YOUR GARBAGE.
(別忘了滅火和帶走垃圾)
TEMPERATURES CAN CHANGE QUICKLY,
(由於氣溫可能會急速變化) (記得事先確認天氣預報)
WEAR WARM CLOTHING IF NECESSARY TO PREVENT COLD.
(必要時穿著保暖衣物防寒)